{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "A boy named Chanco saved this city from a native raid by warning his caregiver, Richard Pace, of the impending attack. In the opening days of the Civil War, William Allen raised a private pro-Confederate militia to occupy this site to block the Union from reaching Richmond downstream. This city was partially razed in the midst of Bacon's Rebellion, and the House of Burgesses was originally set up in this settlement prior to its relocation to Williamsburg. A Stuart king names, for ten points, which first permanent English settlement in North America?",
      "answer": "Jamestown"
    },
    {
      "question": "All three daughters of one ruler of this name were accused of adultery in the Tour de Nesle [NEH-luh]] Affair. One ruler of this name sent his son Louis to go on the Albigensian Crusade. That ruler with this name crushed the English at the Battle of Bouvines [[boo- VEEN]]. A Spanish ruler of this name invaded the Netherlands in the Eighty Years’ War, and that ruler of this name formed a fleet with the aim of deposing Elizabeth I that was defeated at Gravelines [[grav-LEEN]]. For ten points, give this name of the king who created the Spanish Armada.",
      "answer": [
        "Philip",
        "Philip IV",
        "Philip II of France",
        "Philip II of Spain",
        "Felipe",
        "Philippe in place of Philip"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Black Panthers inspired a party composed and named for this group which led a renaissance of Maharashtra-based literature and fine arts in the 1970s. The term Harijan, which translates to \"Children of God,\" was used to refer to this group of people in the early 20th century. Under the influence of Rajiv Gandhi, one parliament passed the Prevention of Atrocities Act in an attempt to halt discrimination against this class of people. Mohandas Gandhi was an advocate for, for ten points, which ostracized class of the Indian caste system?",
      "answer": [
        "Untouchables",
        "the Dalits",
        "the Scheduled Caste",
        "the Dalit Panthers"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A crossbowmen who may have practiced this discipline shot and killed Richard the Lionheart during a siege of Chalus in France. Caelius Apicius [[ah-PIH-kee-us]] wrote a work in this field in Vulgar Latin which opens with the chapter Epimeles, or \"The Careful Housekeeper.\" Gervase Markham wrote a work in this discipline named The English Housewife, including a chapter titled \"Banqueting Stuff.\" De re culinaria is a pamphlet on, for ten points, what discipline which involves preparing food?",
      "answer": [
        "Cooking",
        "Gastronomy",
        "Culinary arts before \"culinaria\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s body was allegedly placed in a glass coffin, but a team of forensic scientists discovered it was incorrectly identified. After this man executed the loser of the Battle of Cajamarca [[kah-hah-MAHR-kah]], this man had two sons with his widow, renamed Dona Angelina. This man’s life ended when supporters of Diego de Almagro's son stormed a palace and assassinated him, making Almagro the new Governor of Peru. For ten points, name this conquistador who founded Lima after destroying the Inca Empire.",
      "answer": "Francisco Pizarro or Francisco Pizarro González"
    },
    {
      "question": "Queen Elizabeth II granted this title to Margot Fonteyn after her performance as the Queen of Air in Homage to the Queen. Following an international tour with the Kirov company, American Eva Evdokimova [[ehv-DOH-kee-MOH-vah]] was given the assoluta form of this designation. The solo dance known as The Dying Swan was originated by a person with this specific designation, Anna Pavlova, who held the title while a member of Ballet Russes [[ROOSE]]. The most talented and experienced ballet dancers in a company are given, for ten points, which designation?",
      "answer": "Prima ballerina"
    },
    {
      "question": "This thinker was invited to a feast by Emperor Frederick II, to whom this man dedicated his Book of Squares. For his technical work, like solving several problems by Johannes of Palermo, this man was granted a lifetime salary by his home city of Pisa. This man's work Liber Abaci popularized Indo-Arabic numerals in the western world, as well as a biologically relevant namesake series of numbers. For ten points, name this medieval Italian mathematician whose namesake \"sequence\" begins, \"0, 1, 1, 2, 3.\"",
      "answer": [
        "Fibonacci",
        "Leonardo Bonacci",
        "or Leonardo of Pisa",
        "or Leonardo Bigano Pisano",
        "Fibonacci Numbers",
        "or Fibonacci Sequence"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man publicly protested segregation by sharing a small pool with an African- American character, Officer Clemmons, in a 1969 episode of his namesake series. This man quoted that show by saying \"What Do You Do with the Mad that You Feel?\" in an argument to save funding for PBS while testifying in front of the Senate Subcommittee of Communications in 1969. The opening theme \"Won't You Be My Neighbor?\" was written by, for ten points, which host of a long-running children's TV show about [this man's] Neighborhood?",
      "answer": [
        "Fred Rogers",
        "Mister Rogers",
        "Mister Rogers' Neighborhood"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During this event, the generals Aleksei Peshchurov [[pehsh-CHOO-roff]] and Lovell Rousseau oversaw a flag transfer ceremony in the town of New Archangel. The extinction of a local sea otter population and the monetary deficit experienced after the Crimean War led to this event, which was negotiated by Eduard de Stoeckl [[STOW-kuhl]]. Detractors of this action dubbed it both \"Seward's Icebox\" and \"Seward's Folly.\" For ten points, name this acquisition by the Andrew Johnson administration of a Russian colony in North America.",
      "answer": [
        "Alaska Purchase or Purchase of Alaska",
        "synonymous answers like Buying Alaska",
        "Prodazha Alyaski",
        "or Sale of Alaska"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In a work in this language, the eardstapa, or \"Wanderer,\" is in self-imposed exile after losing his lord and fellow retainers during a raid. The long form poem The Age of Anxiety by W.H. Auden is in this specific language, emulating an early style of alliterative verse. The limbs of a monster named Grendel are taken off in a mead hall by the title hero of an epic poem in this language. The poem Beowulf is written in, for ten points, which medieval language of the British isles influenced by Old Norse?",
      "answer": "Old English"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This president repealed the Glass-Steagall Act, citing it was \"no longer appropriate.\" This president signed a law mandating background checks on firearms purchases, the Brady Bill, and dealt with \"Troopergate\" when several officers from his home state alleged they had arranged romantic liaisons for him. This president's Whitewater scandals merged with another scandal in which he claimed to have not had \"sexual relations with that woman.\" For ten points, name this Democratic president during the 1990s who was impeached for perjury for lying about his affair with Monica Lewinsky.",
        "answer": "Bill Clinton or William Jefferson Clinton"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Clinton nominated two Supreme Court justices, Stephen Breyer, and this late justice who died in September 2020.",
        "answer": [
          "Ruth Bader Ginsberg",
          "RBG"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Excessive flooding in this city in 1927 led to the training ship known as the President to float down its streets. The use of low quality coal and the occurrence of an \"anticyclone\" led to the 1952 \"Great Smog\" in this city, killing 4,000 people. Three disease outbreaks were studied by John Snow in this city during its \"Great Stink\" period. A buildup of waste on the Thames [[TEMZ]] occurred in, for ten points, which English capital?",
        "answer": "London"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "John Snow's breakthroughs in epidemiology occurred through studies of what water- borne disease that causes diarrhea and extreme dehydration?",
        "answer": [
          "Cholera",
          "Vibrio cholerae"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A monarch from this dynasty patronized the Fatawa 'Alamgiri law code as part of a personal religious revival that included becoming a hafiz. This dynasty, which was the last regime to destroy the Vishwanath Temple, scaled back religious tolerance by executing Tegh Bahadur, a Sikh guru, and reinstituting the jizya tax under its emperor Aurangzeb. For ten points, name this Muslim dynasty that ruled north India following the 1520s conquests of Babur.",
        "answer": "Mughal Dynasty or the Mughals"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the 1640s, the Mughals began to lose control of huge portions of central India when the Hindu king Shivaji established which empire based in the Deccan Plateau and came to dominate much of central and northern India?",
        "answer": "Maratha Empire or Maratha Confederacy"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man earned the ire of the internet after a tweet resurfaced of him saying, \"Nothing sadder than a hot person in a wheelchair\" in reference to disability activist Rebecca Cokely. After a streak of early 2000s television appearances, this man was approached by Harry Reid and Chuck Schumer to run for the U.S. Senate from Utah. This man defeated both Brad Rutter and James Holzhauer in a special tournament dubbed \"The Greatest of All Time.\" The longest streak in Jeopardy! history is held by, for ten points, which game show contestant?",
        "answer": "Ken Jennings or Kenneth Wayne Jennings III"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What computer system developed by IBM defeated both Rutter and Jennings in a special series of Jeopardy!, winning the million dollar prize?",
        "answer": "Watson"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During the first Easter festivities celebrated on Cebu [[SEE-boo]], this European formed a blood compact with the local tribal head, Rajah Humabon. Legendarily, Chief Lapu- Lapu slew this man with a traditional bolo knife during the Battle of Mactan. This man, who sailed under the Spanish flag, named the Pacific Ocean in the 1520s while leading an expedition to the East Indies. For ten points, name this Portuguese explorer whose crew completed the first circumnavigation of the globe.",
        "answer": [
          "Ferdinand Magellan",
          "Fernão de Magalhães",
          "or Fernando de Magallanes"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Lapu-Lapu was a chieftain of Mactan, in the Visayas group of which East Asian archipelago which was controlled by the Spanish until 1898?",
        "answer": [
          "Philippines",
          "Filipinas",
          "or Pilipinas",
          "Philippine Islands",
          "Archipelago"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The American company Hobby Lobby illegally purchased artifacts from this modern nation through dealers in the United Arab Emirates to populate their Museum of the Bible. Archeologist Gertrude Bell first excavated the Al-Ukhaidir [[ook-\"HIGH\"-deer]] Fortress in this nation, which was built by Caliph Isa ibn Musa to defend the Abbasid city of Karbala. The World Heritage site known as Ashur lies in, for ten points, which modern nation of the Middle East, governed from Baghdad?",
        "answer": "Republic of Iraq"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The city of Babylon contained an ancient \"Gate\" dedicated to which Mesopotamian goddess of love who attempts to woo Gilgamesh in an ancient epic?",
        "answer": [
          "Ishtar",
          "Ishtar Gate",
          "Inanna"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Many performers in these productions, which had a second-act olio, cribbed material from a New Orleans vendor named Old Corn Meal. Fixed roles in these productions included Mr. Tambo, Mr. Bones, and the interlocutor. A popular group that staged these productions was named for Edwin Pearce Christy and incorporated the music of Stephen Foster. For ten points, name this genre of racially charged 19th-century live variety shows in which performers often wore blackface.",
        "answer": "Minstrel shows or minstrelsy"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1859, Virginia Minstrels troupe leader Daniel Decatur Emmett wrote this song, whose common version urges listeners in the title place to \"look away.\"",
        "answer": "\"Dixie\""
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "It's not alchemists, but people of this profession were rounded up and killed by Louis XIV's officials during the Affair of the Poisons. It's not magicians, but escape-artist Harry Houdini undertook a campaign funded by the Scientific American to debunk these figures. The Pythia was a priestess of Apollo who specifically did this job. Pliny the Elder is the first historian to mention the use of a crystal ball used by magi in this position. The use of divination is done by, for ten points, what specific people who claim to prophesize the future?",
        "answer": [
          "Fortune-Tellers",
          "Psychics",
          "or Mediums",
          "or Oracles",
          "descriptions of people with precognition",
          "the ability to see the future"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Pythia served as the head of an Oracle in which Phocian city considered the center of the Earth by the Ancient Greeks?",
        "answer": [
          "Delphi",
          "Pytho"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Battle of the Alamo",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Alamo, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Modern day U.S. state where the Battle of the Alamo was fought.",
          "answer": "Texas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mexican dictator who captured the Alamo.",
          "answer": "Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna"
        },
        {
          "question": "Future President of the Lone Star Republic who sent artillery to reinforce the Alamo.",
          "answer": "Sam Houston"
        },
        {
          "question": "Original purpose of the Alamo prior to its use as a fort before the battle.",
          "answer": [
            "Spanish Mission",
            "Christian Mission",
            "or Mission Station",
            "Station for Missionaries"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "\"King of the Wild Frontier\" and Tennessee representative who died at the Alamo alongside James Bowie.",
          "answer": "Davy Crockett"
        },
        {
          "question": "South Carolinian lieutenant colonel who professionalized the republic's army and commanded the soldiers at the Alamo.",
          "answer": "William Barrett Travis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Panic caused by the fall of the Alamo, leading to an evacuation of the city of San Antonio.",
          "answer": "\"Runaway Scrape\""
        },
        {
          "question": "Tennessee woman who, with her daughter Angelina, were the only two Anglo- Americans to survive the Alamo disaster.",
          "answer": "Susanna Dickinson"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Norway",
      "prompt": "Concerning the nation of Norway, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital of Norway established as a trading outpost in 1048 by Harald Hardrada.",
          "answer": "Oslo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Fuel resource which Norway led Europe in producing in the 1990s due to the expansion of North Sea platforms.",
          "answer": "Crude Oil or Petroleum"
        },
        {
          "question": "Viking Explorer and father of Leif who founded the first Norse settlement in Greenland.",
          "answer": [
            "Erik the Red or Eirik Raude",
            "Erik Thorvaldsson"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "14th to 16th century \"Union\" of Norway, Sweden, and Denmark.",
          "answer": "Kalmar Union or Kalmarunionen"
        },
        {
          "question": "Norwegian explorer, the first man to lead an expedition to reach the South Pole.",
          "answer": "Roald Amundsen or Roald Engelbregt Gravning Amundsen"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nazi collaborator who led German-occupied Norway and whose name became synonymous with \"traitor.\"",
          "answer": "Vidkun Quisling or Vidkun Abraham Lauritz Jonssøn Quisling"
        },
        {
          "question": "Arctic island, once known as Spitsbergen, which Norway was given sovereignty over by a 1920s League of Nations treaty.",
          "answer": "Svalbard"
        },
        {
          "question": "King of Denmark and Norway who fought in the Thirty Years War and lends his name to the old name for Norway's capital.",
          "answer": [
            "King Christian IV",
            "Christiania"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Zimbabwe",
      "prompt": "Concerning Zimbabwe, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital of Zimbabwe, known as Salisbury under British rule.",
          "answer": "Harare"
        },
        {
          "question": "South African people whose chief Mzilikazi established his personal kingdom in Zimbabwe following a rebellion against his kin, Shaka.",
          "answer": "Zulu or amaZulu"
        },
        {
          "question": "Economic effect experienced by the Zimbabwean dollar which led to its virtual abandonment in the 2000s.",
          "answer": "Hyperinflation"
        },
        {
          "question": "President of Zimbabwe who ruled for thirty years beginning in 1980.",
          "answer": "Robert Mugabe or Robert Gabriel Mugabe"
        },
        {
          "question": "British businessman and owner of De Beers diamond company who once named Zimbabwe.",
          "answer": [
            "Cecil Rhodes or Cecil John Rhodes",
            "Rhodesia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Party which has ruled Zimbabwe since its independence.",
          "answer": "ZANU-PF"
        },
        {
          "question": "White prime minister of what is now Zimbabwe who fought communist-backed Black nationalist guerrillas during the Bush War.",
          "answer": "Ian Smith or Ian Douglas Smith"
        },
        {
          "question": "1979 \"Agreement\" which ended the destructive Bush War, establishing an independent and Black-led Zimbabwe.",
          "answer": "Lancaster House Agreement"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A false bomb threat was leveraged by this national government to arrest dissident journalist Raman Pratasevich in June 2021. Opposition leader Sergei (20 pts)",
        "Tikhanovsky [[teek-hah-NOHV-skee]] was sentenced to jail for eighteen years in response to his plan to challenge a president of this country seeking his sixth term. The Anti-Cockroach Movement opposed longtime president Alexander (10 pts)",
        "Lukashenko [[loo-kah-SHEN-koh]] in, for ten points, what Eastern European nation governed from Minsk?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Republic of Belarus or Respublika Belarus",
        "Byelorussia"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Tom Clark once commissioned a list of 12,000 disloyal citizens from this man. This man first led the \"Radical Division\" during the Palmer Raids and had a public dispute with T.R.M. Howard over the lethargic (20 pts)",
        "police response to Southern lynchings. Starting in 1956, this man authorized a wide-ranging program of partially illegal infiltration and disinformation called (10 pts)",
        "COINTELPRO [[koh-IHN-tel- pro]], which targeted the Black Panthers and Martin Luther King. For ten points, name this man who served from 1924 to his 1972 death as the director of the FBI and its precursors."
      ],
      "answer": "J. Edgar Hoover or John Edgar Hoover"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Position and nation required. During the Hague Secret Emissary Affair, the last man in this position attempted to assert his right to sovereign diplomacy despite its official loss in the Eulsa Treaty of 1905. This position is symbolically represented by the Phoenix (20 pts)",
        "Throne, and it was legendarily established by Dangun according to the Gogi [[GOH-gee]]. The hangul (10 pts)",
        "writing system was invented by a man in this position named Sejong the Great. For ten points, name this regal position held for five centuries by the Joseon Dynasty."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Monarch of Korea",
        "Ruler, King,",
        "Emperor in place of \"Monarch\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In Medieval England, the eggs of this specific animal were fed to children to ward off drunkenness and as a cure to blindness. One of these animals named Ko'Ko, or the \"Watcher of the dark,\" is the underworld deity of the Hopi. A contingent of this specific bird flying over the battle site of (20 pts)",
        "Salamis signaled a Greek victory over the Persians according to Plutarch. The Athenian tetradrachma depicts this (10 pts)",
        "bird and symbol of the city on its backside. For ten points, name this bird which symbolized wisdom in Ancient Greece and is associated with Athena."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Owls or Strigiformes",
        "Athene noctua",
        "or Owl of Athena",
        "Owl of Minerva"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this city, a man who removed his shoes to reveal black socks wore a beaded necklace representing victims of lynching and the slave trade. An event in this city was planned by the (20 pts)",
        "OPHR, an organization co-founded by Harry Edwards. Wearing black gloves, Tommie Smith and John Carlos made a raised-fist gesture in this city while \"The Star-Spangled Banner\" played. American and Australian athletes displayed Black Power (10 pts)",
        "symbols at the 1968 Summer Olympics held in, for ten points, what capital city?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Mexico City",
        "Ciudad de México"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man wrote a romanticized account of the Covenanters victory at Loudon Hill in his novel Old Mortality. The lynching of the title man in the historical Porteous [[POHR-shus]] Riots in Edinburgh acts as the backdrop for this man's novel, (20 pts)",
        "The Heart of the Midlothian. In another novel by this man, the title Anglo-Saxon pretends to be the Spanish knight Desdichado to win a (10 pts)",
        "tournament presided over by King John. Rowena is married to the title knight at the behest of Richard the Lionheart in, for ten points, what author's novel Ivanhoe?"
      ],
      "answer": "Walter Scott"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Johann Gustav Droysen wrote the seven volume work The History of [this state's] Politics and led it's namesake school of historiography in the 19th century. The treatise On (20 pts)",
        "War was written by a military theorist and general from this kingdom, Carl von Clausewitz. Count Mirabeau [[me-rah-BOH]] once stated this kingdom was \"not a state with a (10 pts)",
        "military, but a military with a state.\" For ten points, name this early modern state which united Germany in the 19th century under the leadership of Otto von Bismarck."
      ],
      "answer": "Kingdom of Prussia or Königreich Preussen"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) While in prison for supposedly perpetrating this violent event, German- American Louis Lingg killed himself with a blast cap hidden in a cigar rather than going to trial. Men arrested during this event are labelled (20 pts)",
        "\"Mad Dogs\" in a contemporary political cartoon where they attack a personification of the U.S. after being set free by Governor John Altgeld. Albert Parsons claimed a Pinkerton agent threw the (10 pts)",
        "dynamite which began this violent labor demonstration. Agitation for the eight-hour workday led to violence in, for ten points, what Chicago riot of the late 1880s?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Haymarket Square Riot",
        "Haymarket Affair",
        "or Haymarket Massacre"
      ]
    }
  ]
}